Preliminary guide to the Frederick Gutheim papers, 1952-1980 MS0244.UA
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Frederick Gutheim papers
1952-1980
Special Collections Research Center, The George Washington University
Gutheim, Frederick Albert
MS0244.UA
4 Linear Feet
Frederick Albert Gutheim (1908-1993) was a city planner, urban historian and architectural critic, and professor at The George Washington University from 1971-79, and director of the University's graduate program in historic preservation from 1976-1979. Collection include correspondence, papers, publications, exams, syllabi, lecture notes, newsletters, and news clippings ranging from 1952-1980.
Box UP0005
Box UP0006
Box UP0007
Acquisition Information
The collection was donated to University Archives around 1981. Another donation of boxes 5-8 came at a later date.
Biographical Note
Frederick Albert Gutheim (1908-1993) was a city planner, urban historian and architectural critic, and professor at The George Washington University from 1971-79, and director of the University's graduate program in historic preservation from 1976-79.
Mr. Guthheim was born in Cambridge, Massachusetts on March 3, 1908. He received his Bachelor of Arts degree in 1931 from the University of Wisconsin. He continued his studies at the Ecole des Hautes Etudes Urbaines, the London School of Economics and Political Science, and the University of Heidelberg. From 1933 to 1936 he studied at the University of Chicago.
Gutheim was a junior staff member of the Institute for Government Research at the Brookings Institution in Washington, DC. He became an adjunct professor of American History and Civilization, urban and regional planning at George Washington University in 1971. He served on the U.S. Capitol Master Plan Group, the President's Commission, the AIA Interior Department Task Force on the Potomac and as a member of many federal and local planning bodies concerned with the city and the region.
He attended the third conference of the Planning History Group in Dublin, Ireland in 1982, and participated in a traveling seminar at the invitation of the Architecture Society of the People's Republic of China. In addition, he gave the Honor's Day Address to the Clemson University School of Architecture on April 10, 1983, and received an award of merit from the American Association for State and Local History for his achievement as initiator and chairman of the Sugarloaf Regional Trails.
Gutheim's writing career began in 1931 when he became a contributing editor for the American Magazine of Art. In 1948, he became the first architectural writer for the New York Herald Tribune. He later became an architectural critic for The Washington Post and advisory editor for Washingtonian magazine. His articles have appeared in numerous national magazines, such as Nation, Harper's, and Saturday Review. He received a decoration from the President of Finland in 1974 for bringing that country's new town of Tapiola to the attention of the American public.
Dr. Fritz, as he was sometimes called, wrote extensively on architectural subjects and "Washington History: Housing As Environment" (1953); "The Potomac" (1949); "Planning Washington: 1924-1976" (1976); and "Worthy of the Nation: The History of Planning for the National Capital" (1977), to name a few.
Gutheim married Mary Pardon on June 8, 1935 and they had one son. Dr. Gutheim died October 2, 1993 in Washington, D.C.
There are no copyright or literary rights restrictions on it. Note also that an oral history done with Mr. Gutheim in 1977 can be found in MS0371, and other papers of his reside in the Special Collections Department. Other manuscripts can be found at the University of Wyoming.
See also an article in "Washington History" magazine (call number F191.C72; v.10:1)
N.B. This history note was written in 2005
Collection Scope and Content
Frederick Albert Gutheim (1908-1993) was a city planner, urban historian and architectural critic, and professor at The George Washington University from 1971-79, and director of the University's graduate program in historic preservation from 1976-1979. Collection include correspondence, papers, publications, exams, syllabi, lecture notes, newsletters, and news clippings ranging from 1952-1980.
Arrangement
Organized into 4 series: Academic materials, Publications and papers, Urban planning research materials, and Correspondence.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
City planning; Housing; Urbanization; Buildings -- Washington (D.C.); Architecture -- Washington (D.C.); Washington (D.C.); Mount Vernon (Va.: Estate); Transportation -- Washington Metropolitan Area; George Washington University; Gutheim, Frederick Albert; George Washington University. Historic Preservation Program
- Academic materials, 1963-1978; Series 1
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials prepared and used by Frederick Gutheim while serving as a professor and administrator at George Washington University.
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically, followed by undated materials.
  - Notes for Prospectus, 23 January 1971 (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - Notes for an architectural tour of Wash. (American Oil Company, Metropolitan Wash, map), 1963 May - 1964 August (revised) (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - 186. Revision for Fall 1972 (Box 8, Folder 87)
  - 188 Class List (Registrar), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Course Materials Master Set, Urban History 186 [1/2], 1972 (Box 8, Folder 88)
  - Course Materials Master Set, Urban History 186 [2/2], 1972 (Box 8, Folder 89)
  - Housing Legislation Assignment History 188, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - 188 Administration, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - AM CIV 188 Syllabus, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - AM CIV 188 Final Exam, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - 188 Housing (1), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - 188 Housing (2), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - 188 Housing (3), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - 188 Project 1: Newspapers, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 188 Project 4: Population Policies, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - 188 Project 6: Housing as Environment, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - 188 Project 7: Streets, 1973 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - 188 Individual Project, Proposal (3); Project (5), 1973 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 188 Social Structure of Cities, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - AM CIV 188 Police, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - 188 Administration, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - AM CIV 188 Urban Issues, Syllabus, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - AM CIV 188, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Historic Preservation Film Festival, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 47)
  - AMCV 278 (Spr '78) Hist. Pres. Prof. Gutheim National Register 10-300 Forms by HP students, 1978 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Reading/Library (originally within Folder 10), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - AM CIV 188 City Profile Review, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - AM CIV 188: A Walk Around the Block, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - 188 Family History Project, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - 188 Interviewing your Grandmother, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - 188 Immigrant Interview, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - 188 Introduction, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - 188 Urban Growth, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Class Legislation Papers, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - AM CIV 188 Suburbs, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Housing Assignment: At the Site, undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Housing: Reading List, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - 188 Housing, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - AM CIV 188 Poverty, undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - AM CIV 188 Welfare, undated (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - 188 Parks and Urban Amenities, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - AM CIV 188 Public Health in the City, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Washington Course Freshmen, Experimental Humanities, undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - 188 Transportation, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - AM CIV 188 Urban Government, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - 188 Course Outline (last part) and additional reading, undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - History 188, Alvin Sehorr, "Incrementalism", undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Prospectus for a series of guidebooks for American Cities. Prepared for Random House, Jacob Epstein, undated (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Guide to Washington - typescript notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 36)
  - Bibliographical essay assignment on Urban Historians, undated (Box 6, Folder 45)
  - Historic Preservation Program Announcement Letter, undated (Box 6, Folder 46)
  - AM CIV 188 Exams, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 188 Student Information Replies, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Publications and papers, 1960-1973; Series 2
  This series contains materials written by Frederick Gutheim and published or delivered as speeches.
  - Comments on the Washington Transportation program. An address by Frederick Guthiem, Washington Center for Metropolitan Studies, presented to the Regional Science Assoc. meeting, St. Louis, Missouri, 1960 December 30 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - "A Manuscript Directory of Recent Films on the Urban Environment", by Frederick Gutheim (bound volume), 1967 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Poolesville Hearing on the Rural Zone Statement of Frederick Gutheim, 7 August 1973 (Box 6, Folder 60)
  - To the Montgomery County Board of Appeals, 4 October 1973 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Frederick Gutheim Resume, undated (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Community Planning Nazi Germany - typescript notes, undated (Box 6, Folder 37)
  - II. Satisfaction in the Work Place p. 21-40, 92-96 by F.A. Gutheim, undated (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Book review notes, undated (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous manucript notes 1 page, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Manuscript Notes on restaurant placement, undated (Box 6, Folder 71)
- Urban planning research materials, 1952-1973; Series 3
  This series contains materials collected by Frederick Gutheim during his career as an academic, administrator, and professional in the discipline of Urban Planning and Historic Preservation. Included are clippings, publications and books by other authors, pamphlets, seminar agendas, type- and hand-written notes, and addresses.
  - Reviews forms and functions twentieth century architecture, Edited by Talbot Hamlin Four volumes New York Columbia University Press $75.00, 1952 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Table of Contents for Tokyo: Its Socio-Economic Analysis, by Tokue Shibata, Iwanami, Tokyo, Japan, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - New Architecture in Washington Wurster Itinerary. Revised, 1961 September 1 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Mumford Lewis, "The Future of the City", 1962-1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Japanese Sources in Metropolitan and Related Affairs, 23 September 1963 (Box 6, Folder 80)
  - City Md. Regional Planning in Washington A Guided Tour for Visitors, August 1964 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Urban Vitality to John Anderson (Vice Karl Meyer) Washington Post editorial page, 1964 November 23 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Urban Issues, (a) Post, 15 September 1966 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Urban Issues, (b) Post, 15 September 1966 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Pamphlet: Maryland History Notes, 1971 (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - Records of the Columbia Historical Society of Washington, D.C. 1969-1970, Edited with an introduction by Francis Coleman Rosenberger. Published by the society, Washington, D.C. $15.00, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Past Proposals for the Potomac Piedmont, 24 April 1971 (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Potomac Environment Controversies: Pepco Power Plant at Dickerson newspaper clippings, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Potomac Environment Controversies: Advanced Wastewater Treatment Newspaper Clippings, 1973 (Box 6, Folder 82)
  - East Coast Trip, 03/1973 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Memorandum of Briefing Session on the Environmental Situation in Western Montgomery, 18 September 1973 (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - Various Papers from a Rural Regeneration Seminar in Bristol, 30-31 May 1979 (Box 6, Folder 81)
  - Urban History Bibliographies, undated (Box 8, Folder 86)
  - Montgomery County Historical Society, undated (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - Montgomery County Upper County Planning, Housing, and Community Development, undated (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - Notes on Hood College Field Study Program on the Potomac, undated (Box 6, Folder 74)
  - The Potomac Piedmont Center, undated (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - A Proposed List, undated (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Statement on Frederick Process (Chadwick Property) Rezoning, undated (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Proceedings before Maryland Public Service Commission in re PEPCO Expansion at Dickerson, undated (Box 6, Folder 59)
  - Poolesville Historic District, undated (Box 6, Folder 53)
  - Further Questions Raised by the Growth of New Towns and Communities in Metropolitan Washington, undated (Box 6, Folder 52)
  - Comments on Reston History [Transcript], undated (Box 6, Folder 51)
  - Reston, undated (Box 6, Folder 49)
  - Sugarloaf Regional Trails, undated (Box 6, Folder 48)
  - Gutheim Personal Papers - Review - Talbot Hamlin, undated (Box 6, Folder 40)
  - Building Support Systems, undated (Box 6, Folder 39)
  - Practice in Revitalization of Urban Centre (Annapolis, Maryland), undated (Box 6, Folder 38)
  - A Fatal Beauty; Chesapeake Horizons; The Potomac: American Reflections, undated (Box 8, Film 92)
  - Mahony, Marion Lucy -biography, undated (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Errata list, undated (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Cosmos Club receipt, undated (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Potomac Environment controversies Pepco Power Plant at Dickerson Environmental Evaluation report by Johns Hopkins U. Ches. Bay Inst.``, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - A greater measure of definition..., undated (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Office Landscaping, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper clippings, photocopies, re: urban and rural housing (c), undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Newspaper clippings, photocopies, re: urban and rural housing (b), undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Newspaper clippings, photocopies, re: urban and rural housing (a), undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Newspaper clippings re: urban and rural housing (b), undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper clippings re: urban and rural housing (a), undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Incompletes, undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Urban Planning: the Future of Cities, undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Metropolitan Boston: Wakstein, "Boston's Search for a Metropolitan Solution", undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Rings, bosses and immigrant groups, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Public Education, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - The Evolution of the Health Maintenance Organization, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Health Maintenance Organization, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Urban Homesteading--Wilmington, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Housing: Forest Hills, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Housing: New York City, Lower East Side, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Suburbs/Metropolis, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Urban Growth Policy (AIA), undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Migration and Urban Growth, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Population and Urbanization, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Correspondence, 1953-1980; Series 4
  This series contains correspondence to and from Frederick Guthiem.
  - Correspondence: miscellaneous, 1939-1978 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence: Alfred A. Knopf and Frederick Gutheim, 1952 July 29 - August 14 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Correspondence: Perspectives USA, February 1953 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Memorandum To: Project file on senic areas From: Frederick Gutheim, 1965 January 19 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence: Mrs. Robert Simon to Gutheim, 25 February 1966 (Box 6, Folder 50)
  - Correspondence: Paule Anglim and Frederick Gutheim, 1968 January 9 - January 12 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Correspondence: Frederick Gutheim and Catherine S. Chilman, 17 Feburary 1971 - 23 April 1971 (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Correspondence: William Wilson Atkin to Frederick Gutheim, 3 March 1971 (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Correspondence: Frederick Gutheim and C. N. Murphy, 8-10 March 1971 (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Correspondence: Gutheim to Robert Dennis, 2 April 1971 (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Correspondence: Frederick Gutheim and Ralph B. Tucker, 28 June 1972 - 5 July 1972 (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - Correspondence: Frederick Gutheim to William Sher, 31 December 1972 (Box 6, Folder 56)
  - Correspondence: Miscellaneous [1/2], 1972 (Box 8, Folder 90)
  - Correspondence: Miscellaneous [2/2], 1972 (Box 8, Folder 91)
  - Correspondence: Frederick Gutheim to Edmund F. Rovner, Department of Economic and Community Development, 18 June 1973 (Box 6, Folder 58)
  - Correspondence: Frederick Gutheim to Blair Lee III, 26 July 1973 (Box 6, Folder 57)
  - Correspondence: Frederick Gutheim to Commissioners of Poolesville, 4 September 1973 (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Correspondence: Frederick Gutheim to the Montgomery County Board of Appeals, 4 October 1973 (Box 6, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence: to Sidney Bloom, subject: wirescape, 3 November 1973 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence: Offutt, Haugh and Bloom, P.A., 7 November 1973 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Potomac Environment controversies Pepco Power Plant at Dickerson correspondence, testimony, 1973 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Potomac Environment Controversies; Advanced Wastewater Treatment -- correspondence, agendas, reports, 1973 (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Correspondence: Frederick Gutheim to David Wallace, 25 February 1976 (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Correspondence Roberta Hahn re: Trimble House, 2 October 1980 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence to Gutheim from the Phelps, undated (Box 6, Folder 35)
  - Correspondence between Sarah and Gutheim, undated (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Correspondence: Frederick Guthiem and Mme. Radford, undated (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Correspondence: Frederick Gutheim to David Wallace, undated (Box 6, Folder 54)
  - Correspondence: Frederick Gutheim to James L. Kunen, undated (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Correspondence: Professional Visitors to Washington, undated (Box 6, Folder 44)
  - Christmas and New Year card. from the Carnegies, undated (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Montgomery County Historic Pres. correspondence, undated (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Various Business Cards, undated (Box 6, Folder 79)